Ben Cunningham Papers
Ben Cunningham Papers
1904-1969
Cunningham, Ben, 1904-1975
2.25 linear ft.
Spanning 1904 to 1969, the Ben Cunningham Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the American painter and art educator (1904-1975). The collection, which is heavily annotated by Cunningham, illuminates a professional career which encompassed WPA Federal Art Project mural work as well as the op art movement of the mid to late 1960s. Some of the items in the collection have been restricted to prevent their further deterioration. Photocopies of these embrittled items have been made available for researcher use.
149597
Biographical History
American painter, muralist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 1-2) contains incoming letters and outgoing carbon copies of Cunningham's replies, together with a variety of other related documents. The correspondence, predominantly from the 1960s, is generally of a professional nature, and includes that with artists (Abe Ajay, Will Barnet, Hannes Beckmann, Lawrence Campbell, David Diao, Peggy Dixon, Florence Fanshel, Robert Gwathmey, Hein Heckroth, Carl Holty, Avery Johnson, Sandy Lerner, Raeford Liles, Herman Maril, Roy Slade, Jeffrey Steele, Jean Varda); authors (Faber Birren, Warren Bower, Dorothy Caffrey, Donald G. Carraher, Susan Fanshel, Nathan Israeli, Mary McChesney, Sterling McIlhany, Aldo Pellegrini, William N. Robson); and clients (Goran Bauer, David Bermant, Cadence Records, Mark Johnson, John and Kate Prutting, Springbok Editions). Organizational correspondence focuses upon Cunningham's work in connection with art galleries and museums (Larry Aldrich Museum Foundation, Castellane Gallery, East Hampton Gallery, Georgia Museum of Art, Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, Hecksher Museum, Museum of Modern Art, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Riverside Museum, Triangle Gallery, Tweed Gallery, Whitney Museum of American Art); educational institutions (Art Students League of New York, Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, Morgan State College, Pratt Institute, University of Minnesota); and professional organizations (Artists for CORE, Artists for SEDF, Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, Society of Industrial Artists and Designers). An exchange (1965-1967) with the New York State Attorney General documents Cunningham's interest in legislation regarding the artist/dealer relationship.
Artwork (Box 2) includes photographs of Cunningham's work, a jigsaw puzzle, record album art, and miscellaneous reproductions used for advertising as well as book and periodical illustrations and cover designs. Arranged by the title of work supplied by Cunningham, the Photographs of paintings bear further annotations providing the year of the piece's production and the name of its purchaser. Photographs also document exhibitions at San Francisco's Raymond & Raymond Gallery and at the Riverside Museum in New York.
Autobiographical material, the transcript of an interview for the Archives of American Art on Cunningham's WPA experience, a lecture before the Art Students League, lists of paintings, a memorandum relating to the faculty at the Cooper Union, and an assortment of statements, some dictated, about his work constitute Writings (Box 2).
Memorabilia (Boxes 2-3) consists of photographs and printed material. Among the photographs are portraits (1904-1967) and images of Cunningham in his studio and lecturing before a Cooper Union design class. Printed material comprises articles and reviews (1965-1969), clippings (1941-1969), exhibition catalogs and invitations (1960-1969), and teaching-related items, including course catalogs and An Aspect of Illusion, a Cooper Union student publication which explores the technical features of op art as it relates to human perception.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Ajay, Abe.; Barnet, Will, 1911-2012.; Bauer, Göran, 1923-; Bermant, David.; Birren, Faber, 1900-1988.; Bower, Warren.; Caffrey, Dorothy Cruickshank.; Campbell, Lawrence, 1914-1998.; Coates, Robert M. (Robert Myron), 1897-1973.; Crump, Iris M.; Cunningham, Ben, 1904-1975.; Diao, David, 1943-; Dixon, Peggy.; Fanshel, Susan.; Gwathmey, Robert, 1903-1988.; Heckroth, Hein.; Holty, Carl, 1900-1973.; Hughes-Stanton, Corin.; Israeli, Nathan, 1906-; Johnson, Avery, 1965-; Lewis, Elizabeth Matthew.; Liles, Raeford.; McChesney, Mary.; McIlhany, Sterling.; Maril, Herman.; Mourlot, Fernand.; Neiniger, Urban.; Pellegrini, Aldo.; Riska, Ken F.; Robson, William N.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Slade, Roy.; Tallroth, Tore.; Varda, Jean.; Wechter, Vivienne Thaul.; Federal Art Project.; United States -- Work Projects Administration.; United States -- Works Progress Administration.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists as teachers -- United States.; Color in art.; Federal aid to the arts -- United States.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Optical art.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Announcements.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Interviews.; Invitations.; Jigsaw puzzles.; Lectures.; Memorabilia.; Notes (documents); Photographs.; Transcripts.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Some of the items in the collection have been restricted to prevent their further deterioration. Photocopies of these embrittled items have been made available for researcher use.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ben Cunningham.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - Ajay, Abe, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - [Larry] Aldrich Museum Foundation, Inc. (Ridgefield, Conn.), 1966 (Box 1)
  - Archives of American Art, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Art Students League of New York, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Artforum (San Francisco, Calif.), 1963 (Box 1)
  - Artists for CORE, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Artists for SEDF, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Barnet, Will, 1966; 1967 (Box 1)
  - Bauer, Goran C. H. and Catharina, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Beckmann, Hannes and Elsa, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Bermant, David, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Birren, Faber, 1965; 1967 (Box 1)
  - Bower, Warren, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cadence Records (New York, N.Y.), 1960 (Box 1)
  - Caffrey, Dorothy, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Lawrence, 1967-1969; undated (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Carraher, Donald G., 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Castellane Gallery (Provincetown, Mass.), 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Coates, Robert M., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Community Press (Culpeper, Va.), 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1960-1968; undated (Box 1)
  - Crump, Iris, 1966-1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Diao, David, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Dixon, Peggy, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - East Hampton Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Encampment for Citizenship (New York, N.Y.), 1966 (Box 1)
  - Fanshel, Florence, 1960; 1967 (Box 1)
  - Fanshel, Susan, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, Inc., 1967 (Box 1)
  - [Carl] Fischer Inc., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Georgia Museum of Art, 1967 (Box 1)
  - [Solomon R.] Guggenheim Museum (New York, N.Y.), 1965-1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Gwathmey, Robert, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Harcourt, Brace & World, Inc., 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Heckroth, Hein, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Hecksher Museum (Huntington, New York), 1966 (Box 1)
  - Holty, Carl, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Hughes-Stanton, Corin, See Society of Industrial Artists and Designers (London)
  - Hyatt, Gordon, See WCBS-TV (New York, N.Y.)
  - Israeli, Nathan, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Avery, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Mark, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Kobrick, Florence, See Encampment for Citizenship (New York, N.Y.) (Box 1)
  - Lerner, Sandy, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, Elizabeth Matthew, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Liles, Raeford, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - McChesney, Mary, See Artforum (San Francisco, Calif.)
  - McFarland, Jacqueline, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - McIlhany, Sterling, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Macky, Spencer, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Maril, Herman, 1967; 1969 (Box 1)
  - Morgan State College (Baltimore, Md.), 1960; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Mourlot, Fernand, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Mueller, Cal and Prissy, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.), 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Neininger, Urban and Jean Purcell, 1967 (Box 1)
  - New York (State). Attorney General, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - New York (State). Department of Law, See New York (State). Attorney General
  - New York Art Scene '67, See Encampment for Citizenship (New York, N.Y.)
  - New York Guild of Handweavers, 1967 (Box 1)
  - New York Public Library, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Pellegrini, Aldo, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Pratt Institute (Brooklyn, N.Y.), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Prutting, John and Kate, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Riska, Ken, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Riverside Museum (New York, N.Y.), 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Robson, William N., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, See New York (State). Attorney General
  - Silvermine Publishers, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Slade, Roy, 1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Society of Industrial Artists and Designers (London), 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Springbok Editions Inc., 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Steele, Jeffrey, 1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Tallroth, Tore and Marthe, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Triangle Gallery (San Francisco, Calif.), 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Tweed Gallery (Duluth, Minn.), See University of Minnesota
  - University of Minnesota, 1967-1969; undated (Box 2)
  - University of Texas, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Varda, Jean, 1952-1969; undated (Box 2)
  - WCBS-TV (New York, N.Y.), 1965; 1969 (Box 2)
  - WNYC-TV, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Wechter, Vivienne Thaul, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York, N.Y.), 1960 (Box 2)
  - YM-YWHA of Essex County, 1967 (Box 2)
  - A-Z, unidentified, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Artwork (Reproductions)
  - Photographs
    - By title (A-Z), untitled, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Exhibitions
      - Raymond & Raymond Gallery (San Francisco, Calif.) (Box 2)
      - Riverside Museum (New York, N.Y.) (Box 2)
  - Jigsaw puzzle, "Equivocation II", 1965 (Oversize 1)
    Springbok Editions
  - Record album art for cover, sleeve, 1963; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1933-1969 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Autobiographical statements (Box 2)
  - "Comments on WPA experience", undated (Box 2)
  - Interview, 1964 (Box 2)
    Transcript of Harlan Phillips' interview of Ben Cunningham for the Archives of American Art New Deal and the Arts project
  - Lecture - Art Students League, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Lists of paintings (Box 2)
  - Memorandum - Cooper Union School of Art and Architecture, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Poem - untitled, undated (Box 2)
  - Statements on art -, 1966-1969; undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs
    - Portraits, 1945-1967 (Box 2)
    - Studio, with artwork, 1941-1965 (Box 2)
    - Teaching, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Youth, 1904-1926; with wife - ca. 1950; 2 items (Box 2)
  - Printed material
    - Articles, reviews, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1941-1969 (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs, invitations, 1960-1969; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Teaching-related
      - An Aspect of Illusion (CUAS 9) - Cooper Union School of Art and Architecture, 1963 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, 1965; "Comments on Ben Cunningham and his work" (Box 3)